<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Do Not Disturb My Circles - misc</title><link href="http://donotdisturbmycircles.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://donotdisturbmycircles.com/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://donotdisturbmycircles.com/</id><updated>2022-08-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Inertial forces are intrinsically Galilean</title><link href="http://donotdisturbmycircles.com/inertial-forces-invariant.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Movpasd</name></author><id>tag:donotdisturbmycircles.com,2022-08-01:/inertial-forces-invariant.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The defining property of inertial forces is that they don't affect Galilean invariants: distance and
duration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;em&gt;requires&lt;/em&gt; that they be proportional to mass, but that doesn't fully characterise them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The invariant definition can probably be proven to be equivalent to the more intuitive but arguably
less fundamental definition, that a time-dependent SO(3) transformation can remove them entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can imagine some Galilean spacetime coordinate systems which introduce forces that might be
described as "hyperinertial". These would violate the integrity of rigid bodies -- there's probably
some connection to SO(3) here as well, what with rigid bodies being determined by an element of SO
(3) and a translation from the origin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think Lorentzian relativity can't have inertial forces the way Galilean relativity does.
Invariance of the spacetime interval fixes the Poincaré group (Lorentz group if origin fixed)
completely all on its own, whereas distance and duration &lt;em&gt;doesn't&lt;/em&gt; fix the Galilean group. You need
to impose linearity on top. This must have something to do with the fact that Galilean symmetry
decomposes directly between space and time, whereas Lorentzian only semidirectly.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="short"></category><category term="physics"></category></entry><entry><title>Why multiple time dimensions don't work</title><link href="http://donotdisturbmycircles.com/multiple-time-dimensions.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-07-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-07-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Movpasd</name></author><id>tag:donotdisturbmycircles.com,2022-07-30:/multiple-time-dimensions.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In Lorentzian relativity, the (strict) past and future light cones are totally disjoint, and no
transformation within the part of SO(1, 3) connected with the identity can mix these two sets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This property is so important that this part of SO(1, 3) is sometimes called the "orthochronous"
Lorentz group. It's what guarantees that the causal ordering of events in spacetime is Lorentz
invariant, and thus "objective". (I'm tempted to bet that this also enforces some sort of existence
and uniqueness requirement on Cauchy initial value problems in Lorentzian spacetime, further
formalising the intuition behind causality, but don't quote me on that.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Space does not have such a linear ordering. A rotation continuously connected to the identity in
SO(3) can rotate the +x axis into the -x axis. Therefore, there can be no causal ordering of
events in space. This also reflects our intuition about causality: my left can be your right, but
if a particle's past from my perspective is its future from yours, we will disagree about the
order of causality, which would be a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason space doesn't have such a linear ordering is because there are more than two space
dimensions, which means that you can &lt;em&gt;rotate&lt;/em&gt; space. You can't rotate time alone (in 1+3
dimensions) -- you can only rotate it along with space (Lorentz boosts). The rotation group SO
(1) is trivial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you had more than one time dimension, then you wouldn't really have a spacetime, you'd have a
two conjoined spaces of potentially different dimensions, distinguished by their relative sign
in the metric. Your "time" dimension is nondeterministic. (Again, probably something here about
Cauchy initial value problems, but again, don't quote me on it.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Of course, this ordering is ambiguous as to which direction is future and which is past, and so
doesn't imply an arrow of time. T symmetry still exists.)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="short"></category><category term="physics"></category></entry></feed>